<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE XML SYSTEM "template.dtd">
<XML>
    <xmlHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Creation of the Two Trees of Valinor in the Silmarillion</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p type="license">This file contains texts protected by copyright. They are included
                    solely for the purposes of study and analysis within the framework of an
                    academic exercise. No redistribution or commercial use of these texts is
                    permitted without the authorization of the rights holders.</p>
                <publisher>Maëlys Gioan</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <!-- Tolkien (John Ronald Reuel), Le Silmarillion : histoire des Silmarils, Christopher Tolkien (éd.), Pierre Alien (trad.), Paris, Christian Bourgeois, 1993, pages 30-31. -->
                <bibl type="book" xml:lang="fr">
                    <title>Le Silmarillion : histoire des Silmarils</title>
                    <author>John Ronald Reul Tolkien</author>
                    <editor resp="editor">Christopher Tolkien</editor>
                    <editor resp="translator">Pierre Alien</editor>
                    <publisher>Christan Bourgeois</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
                    <date>1993</date>
                    <biblScope unit="page" from="30" to="31"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <!-- ____________________________________________ ORGANISATION_________________________________________________ -->
                
                
                <listOrg>
                    <org type="race" xml:id="Val_001">
                        <orgName>Valar<addName>Gods</addName></orgName>
                        <link target="https://tolkiengateway.net/wiki/Valar"/>
                        <note>
                            <p>The Valar (sg. Vala) were the Powers of Arda who shaped and ruled the
                                world. They lived on the Western continent of <geogName ref="Ama_001">Aman</geogName>.</p>
                            <p>The Gods is a name wrongly given by Men to the Valar. When the first
                                Edain newly arrived in Beleriand and disputed whether or not to
                                remain, they referred to the Valar as gods in the West.They had not
                                at this point been tutored by the Elves in such high matters.</p>
                        </note>
                    </org>
                    
                    <org type="race" xml:id="Ent_001">
                        <orgName>Ent <addName>Shepherds of the Trees</addName></orgName>
                        <link target="https://tolkiengateway.net/wiki/Ents"/>
                        <note>
                            <p>The Ents were sentient, humanoid beings created at the request of
                                <persName ref="Yav_001">Yavanna</persName> to protect the trees
                                from other creatures, particularly Dwarves,and thus were called
                                "Shepherds of the Trees".</p>
                        </note>
                    </org>
                    
                </listOrg>
                <!-- ____________________________________________ PERSONNES ___________________________________________________ -->
                
                <listPerson>
                    
                    <person xml:id="Yav_001">
                        <persName>Yavanna<addName>Palurien</addName>
                            <addName>Kémi</addName>
                            <addName>Dame de la Terre</addName></persName>
                        <link target="https://tolkiengateway.net/wiki/Yavanna"/>
                        <note>
                            <p>Yavanna Kementári was a <orgName ref="Val_001">Valië</orgName>, the
                                Queen of Earth. Also known as Giver of Fruits, she was responsible
                                for all growing things.</p>
                            <p>Yavanna's surname was Palúrien ("bosom of earth"), a Qenya name, at
                                an earlier stage of writing of The Silmarillion. Kementári first
                                appeared as Kémi from root KEME (Gnomish Címir).</p>
                        </note>
                    </person>
                    
                    <person xml:id="Nie_001">
                        <persName>Nienna</persName>
                        <link target="https://tolkiengateway.net/wiki/Nienna"/>
                        <note>
                            <p>Nienna was a Queen of the <orgName ref="Val_001">Valar</orgName>, the
                                sister of <persName ref="Man_001">Mandos</persName> and <persName
                                    ref="Irm_001">Irmo</persName>, acquainted with grief and sorrow
                                but also pity and courage.</p>
                        </note>
                    </person>
                    
                    <person xml:id="Aul_001">
                        <persName>Aulë</persName>
                        <link target="https://tolkiengateway.net/wiki/Aul%C3%AB"/>
                        <note>
                            <p>Aulë was a <orgName ref="Val_001">Vala</orgName> and one of the
                                Aratar, also known as the Smith and Smith of the <orgName
                                    ref="Val_001">Valar</orgName>, concerned with rock, metal,
                                nature of substances and works of craft.</p>
                        </note>
                    </person>
                    
                    <person xml:id="Van_001">
                        <persName>Vana</persName>
                        <link target="https://tolkiengateway.net/wiki/V%C3%A1na"/>
                        <note>
                            <p>Vána, one of the <orgName ref="Val_001">Valier</orgName>, was the
                                younger sister of <persName ref="Yav_001">Yavanna</persName> and the
                                spouse of Oromë. Among the seven <orgName ref="Val_001">Valier</orgName>, Vána was the sixth
                                named.</p>
                        </note>
                    </person>
                    
                    <person xml:id="Irm_001">
                        <persName>Irmo <addName>Lorien</addName></persName>
                        <link target="https://tolkiengateway.net/wiki/Irmo"/>
                        <note>
                            <p>Irmo, commonly called Lórien after his place of dwelling, was a <persName ref="Val_001">Vala</persName>
                                who was known as "the master of visions and dreams."</p>
                        </note>
                    </person>
                    
                    <person xml:id="Man_001">
                        <persName>Mandos</persName>
                        <link target="https://tolkiengateway.net/wiki/Mandos"/>
                        <note>
                            <p>Mandos was the Doomsman of the <persName ref="Val_001">Valar</persName> who pronounced judgement in
                                matters of fate. He was the keeper of the slain in his Halls in the
                                west of <geogName ref="Val_002">Valinor</geogName>.</p>
                            <p>His actual, less common name was Namo. He was the "elder brother" of
                                the Vala <persName ref="Irm_001">Irmo</persName>. He is one of the Aratar. Together, Mandos and <persName ref="Irm_001">Irmo</persName>
                                are called the Fëanturi ("Masters of Spirits).Their sister is
                                <persName ref="Nie_001">Nienna</persName>. Vairë the Weaver is his wife.</p>
                        </note>
                    </person>
                    
                </listPerson>
                
            </particDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                
                <!-- ____________________________________________ LIEUX ___________________________________________________ -->
                
                <listPlace>
                    <place xml:id="Cer_001" type="building">
                        <geogName>Cercle du Destin <addName>Máhanaxar</addName></geogName>
                        <link target="https://tolkiengateway.net/wiki/M%C3%A1hanaxar"/>
                        <note>
                            <p>Máhanaxar, also called Rithil-Anamo, was the Ring of Doom, probably a
                                hall or court where the <persName ref="Val_001">Valar</persName> held their councils.</p>
                        </note>
                    </place>
                    
                    <place xml:id="Val_002" type="region">
                        <geogName>Valinor</geogName>
                        <link target="https://tolkiengateway.net/wiki/Valinor"/>
                        <note>
                            <p>Valinor or Valinórë was the realm of the <orgName ref="Val_001">Valar</orgName> in central <geogName ref="Ama_001">Aman</geogName>.
                                Valinor was the place to which the <orgName ref="Val_001">Valar</orgName> moved after Almaren was
                                destroyed by Melkor.</p>
                            <p>Valinor properly refers to the inhabited lands of the continent of
                                <geogName ref="Ama_001">Aman</geogName>, home to the <persName ref="Val_001">Valar</persName> and the three kindreds of Elves: the Vanyar,
                                some of the Noldor, and some of the Teleri. Valimar is its central
                                city.</p>
                        </note>
                    </place>
                    
                    <place xml:id="Tel_001" type="tree">
                        <geogName>Telperion <addName>Silpion</addName>
                            <addName>Ninquelote</addName></geogName>
                        <link target="https://tolkiengateway.net/wiki/Telperion"/>
                        <note>
                            <p>Telperion was the elder of the Two Trees of <geogName ref="Val_002">Valinor</geogName>, called the White
                                Tree, which shed silver light on the domain of the <persName ref="Val_001">Valar</persName>. His leaves
                                were of dark green, shining silver beneath, and his boughs were
                                decked with brilliant flowers that shed a rain of silver dew, which
                                was collected as a source of water and of light.</p>
                        </note>
                    </place>
                    
                    <place xml:id="Lau_001" type="tree">
                        <geogName>Laurelin <addName>Lindelokse</addName>
                            <addName>Golden Tree</addName>
                            <addName>Malinalda</addName>
                            <addName>Culurien</addName></geogName>
                        <link target="https://tolkiengateway.net/wiki/Laurelin"/>
                        <note>
                            <p>Laurelin was the Golden Tree of <geogName ref="Ama_001">Aman</geogName>, the female mate of <geogName ref="Tel_001">Telperion</geogName>,
                                and the younger of the Two Trees of Valinor. Laurelin had
                                gold-trimmed leaves and her dew was collected by Varda in her
                                Wells.</p>
                        </note>
                    </place>
                    
                    <place xml:id="Ama_001" type="region">
                        <geogName>Aman</geogName>
                        <link target="https://tolkiengateway.net/wiki/Aman"/>
                        <note>
                            <p>Aman, the Blessed Realm, was a continent that lay to the west of
                                Middle-earth, across the great ocean Belegaer. It contained <geogName ref="Val_001">Valinor</geogName>,
                                the home of the <orgName ref="Val_001">Valar</orgName>, and Eldamar, the kingdom of the
                                Calaquendi.</p>
                        </note>
                    </place>
                    
                    <place xml:id="Kul_001" type="lake">
                        <geogName>Kulullin</geogName>
                        <link target="https://tolkiengateway.net/wiki/Kulullin_and_Silindrin"/>
                        <note>
                            <p>Kulullin and Silindrin were two cauldrons according to the early
                                version of the legendarium in The Book of Lost Tales.</p>
                        </note>
                    </place>
                    
                    <place xml:id="Sil_001" type="lake">
                        <geogName>Silindrin</geogName>
                        <link target="https://tolkiengateway.net/wiki/Kulullin_and_Silindrin"/>
                        <note>
                            <p>Kulullin and Silindrin were two cauldrons according to the early
                                version of the legendarium in The Book of Lost Tales.</p>
                        </note>
                    </place>
                    
                </listPlace>
                
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </xmlHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>Maintenant cela faisait douze heures depuis que <geogName ref="Lau_001"
                        >Lindeloksë</geogName> avait germé, et en cette heure un trait d'argent
                    perça l'éclat de jaune, et voici, les <orgName ref="Val_001">Valar</orgName>
                    virent une pousse s'élever en cet endroit où furent déversés les flots de
                        <geogName ref="Sil_001">Silindrin</geogName>. Son écorce était d'un blanc
                    tendre qui brillait comme des perles et elle poussait aussi vite même que
                    l'avait fait <geogName ref="Lau_001">Laurelin</geogName>, et à mesure qu'elle
                    grandit la splendeur de <geogName ref="Lau_001">Laurelin</geogName> décrût et sa
                    floraison brilla moins, jusqu'à ce que cet arbre-là ne rayonnât que doucement,
                    comme dans le sommeil ; mais voici, l'autre crût maintenant jusqu'à atteindre
                    une stature aussi élevée même que celle de <geogName ref="Lau_001"
                        >Laurelin</geogName>, et son tronc était mieux formé encore et plus élancé,
                    et sa peau comme de la soie, mais ses branchages au-dessus étaient plus épais et
                    plus enchevêtrés et ses tiges plus denses, et ils produisirent une masse de
                    feuilles bleu-vert comme des pointes de lances.</p>

                <p>Alors les <orgName ref="Val_001">Valar</orgName> écarquillèrent les yeux,
                    stupéfaits, mais <persName ref="Yav_001">Palurien</persName> dit :<q
                        who="Yav_001" toWhom="Val_001">"cet arbre n'a encore cessé de pousser"</q>,
                    et voici qu'au moment où elle dit ces mots l'arbre fleurit, et ses fleurs ne
                    pendaient pas en grappes mais étaient comme des fleurs séparées qui poussaient
                    sur des fines tiges qui se balançaient l'une vers l'autre, et qui étaient
                    pareilles à de l'argent et des perles et des étoiles étincelantes et brûlaient
                    d'une lumière blanche ; et il semblait que le coeur de l'arbre battait, et son
                    rayonnement vacillait en cadence, croissant et décroissant. De la lumière comme
                    de l'argent liquide se distillait de son tronc et gouttait sur le sol, et elle
                    répandit une très large illumination de par la plaine, mais qui n'était pourtant
                    pas aussi large que celle de l'<geogName ref="Lau_001">arbre d'or</geogName>, et
                    à cause aussi de ses vastes feuilles et du battement de sa vie intérieure il
                    projetait un continuel flottement d'ombres parmi les mares de son éclat, très
                    nettes et noires ; à ce moment <persName ref="Irm_001">Lorien</persName> ne put
                    contenir sa joie, et même <persName ref="Man_001">Mandos</persName> sourit. Mais
                        <persName ref="Irm_001">Lorien</persName> dit : <q who="Irm_001"
                        toWhom="Val_001">"Voici ! Je vais donner un nom à cet arbre et le nommer
                            <geogName ref="Tel_001">Silpion</geogName>"</q>, et cela a toujours été
                    son nom depuis. Alors <persName ref="Yav_001">Palurien</persName> se leva et dit
                    aux <orgName ref="Val_001">Dieux</orgName> : <q who="Yav_001" toWhom="Val_001"
                        >"Recueillez maintenant toute la lumière qui goutte en forme liquide de ce
                        bel arbre et entreposez-la dans <geogName ref="Sil_001"
                        >Silindrin</geogName>, et ne lui permettez de la quitter qu'avec frugalité.
                        Voici, cet arbre, lorsque les douze heures de sa pleine lumière sont
                        passées, décroîtra à nouveau, et à ce moment la lumière de <geogName
                            ref="Lau_001">Laurelin</geogName> éclatera à nouveau ; mais pour qu'il
                        ne puisse s'épuiser, arrosez-le encore et toujours à partir du chaudron de
                            <geogName ref="Kul_001">Kulullin</geogName> à l'heure où <geogName
                            ref="Tel_001">Silpion</geogName> s'affaiblit, mais à <geogName
                            ref="Tel_001">Silpion</geogName> vous ferez de même, versant à nouveau
                        la lumière recueillie de la profonde <geogName ref="Sil_001"
                            >Silindrin</geogName> à chaque décroissance de l'<geogName ref="Lau_001"
                            >arbre d'or</geogName>. La lumière est la sève de ces arbres et leur
                        sève est lumière ! "</q></p>

                <p>Et avec ces mots elle signifiait que bien que ces arbres dussent être arrosés de
                    lumière pour avoir de la sève et vivre, pourtant de par leur croissance et leur
                    être ils fabriquaient sans cesse de la lumière en grande abondance encore
                    par-dessus et au-delà de ce que leurs racines aspiraient.</p>

            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</XML>
