<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE XML SYSTEM "template.dtd">
<XML>
    <xmlHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <!-- Tolkien (John Ronald Reuel), Le Silmarillion : histoire des Silmarils, Christopher Tolkien (éd.), Pierre Alien (trad.), Paris, Christian Bourgeois, 1993, pages 30-31. -->
                <bibl type="" xml:lang="">
                    <title>Le Silmarillion : histoire des Silmarils</title>
                    <author>John Ronald Reul Tolkien</author>
                    <editor resp="TROUVER">Christopher Tolkien</editor>
                    <!-- trouver un bon rôle pour CT -->
                    <editor resp="translator">Pierre Alien</editor>
                    <publisher>Christan Bourgeois</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
                    <date>1993</date>
                    <biblScope unit="page" from="30" to="31"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>



                <!-- ____________________________________________ ORGANISATION_________________________________________________ -->


                <listOrg>
                    <org type="race" xml:id="Val_001">
                        <orgName>Valar</orgName>
                        <note>
                            <p>The Valar (sg. Vala) were the Powers of Arda who shaped and ruled the
                                world. They lived on the Western continent of Aman.</p>
                            <p>The Gods is a name wrongly given by Men to the Valar. When the first
                                Edain newly arrived in Beleriand and disputed whether or not to
                                remain, they referred to the Valar as gods in the West.They had not
                                at this point been tutored by the Elves in such high matters.</p>
                        </note>
                    </org>

                    <org type="race" xml:id="Ent_001">
                        <orgName>Ent</orgName>
                        <note>
                            <p>The Ents were sentient, humanoid beings created at the request of
                                Yavanna to protect the trees from other creatures, particularly
                                Dwarves,and thus were called "Shepherds of the Trees".</p>
                        </note>
                    </org>

                </listOrg>

                <!-- ____________________________________________ PERSONNES ___________________________________________________ -->

                <listPerson>

                    <person xml:id="Yav_001">
                        <persName>Yavanna</persName>
                        <note>
                            <p>Yavanna Kementári was a Valië, the Queen of Earth. Also known as
                                Giver of Fruits, she was responsible for all growing things.</p>
                            <p>Yavanna's surname was Palúrien ("bosom of earth"), a Qenya name, at
                                an earlier stage of writing of The Silmarillion. Kementári first
                                appeared as Kémi from root KEME (Gnomish Címir).</p>
                        </note>
                    </person>

                    <person xml:id="Nie_001">
                        <persName>Nienna</persName>
                        <note>
                            <p>Nienna was a Queen of the Valar, the sister of Mandos and Irmo,
                                acquainted with grief and sorrow but also pity and courage.</p>
                        </note>
                    </person>

                    <person xml:id="Aul_001">
                        <persName>Aulë</persName>
                        <note>
                            <p>Aulë was a Vala and one of the Aratar, also known as the Smith and
                                Smith of the Valar, concerned with rock, metal, nature of substances
                                and works of craft.</p>
                        </note>
                    </person>

                    <person xml:id="Van_001">
                        <persName>Vana</persName>
                        <note>
                            <p>Vána, one of the Valier, was the younger sister of Yavanna and the
                                spouse of Oromë. Among the seven Valier, Vána was the sixth
                                named.</p>
                        </note>
                    </person>

                </listPerson>
            </particDesc>
            <settingDesc>

                <!-- ____________________________________________ LIEUX ___________________________________________________ -->

                <listPlace>
                    <place xml:id="Cer_001" type="building">
                        <geogName>Cercle du Destin</geogName>
                        <note>
                            <p>Máhanaxar, also called Rithil-Anamo, was the Ring of Doom, probably a
                                hall or court where the Valar held their councils.</p>
                        </note>
                    </place>

                    <place xml:id="Val_002" type="region">
                        <geogName>Valinor</geogName>
                        <note>
                            <p>Valinor or Valinórë was the realm of the Valar in central Aman.
                                Valinor was the place to which the Valar moved after Almaren was
                                destroyed by Melkor.</p>
                            <p>Valinor properly refers to the inhabited lands of the continent of
                                Aman, home to the Valar and the three kindreds of Elves: the Vanyar,
                                some of the Noldor, and some of the Teleri. Valimar is its central
                                city.</p>
                        </note>
                    </place>

                    <place xml:id="Tel_001" type="tree">
                        <geogName>Telperion</geogName>
                        <note>
                            <p>Telperion was the elder of the Two Trees of Valinor, called the White
                                Tree, which shed silver light on the domain of the Valar. His leaves
                                were of dark green, shining silver beneath, and his boughs were
                                decked with brilliant flowers that shed a rain of silver dew, which
                                was collected as a source of water and of light.</p>
                        </note>
                    </place>

                    <place xml:id="Lau_001" type="tree">
                        <geogName>Laurelin</geogName>
                        <note>
                            <p>Laurelin was the Golden Tree of Aman, the female mate of Telperion,
                                and the younger of the Two Trees of Valinor. Laurelin had
                                gold-trimmed leaves and her dew was collected by Varda in her
                                Wells.</p>
                        </note>
                    </place>

                    <place xml:id="Ama_001" type="region">
                        <geogName>Aman</geogName>
                        <note>
                            <p>Aman, the Blessed Realm, was a continent that lay to the west of
                                Middle-earth, across the great ocean Belegaer. It contained Valinor,
                                the home of the Valar, and Eldamar, the kingdom of the
                                Calaquendi.</p>
                        </note>
                    </place>

                    <place xml:id="Kul_001" type="lake">
                        <geogName>Kulullin</geogName>
                        <note>
                            <p>Kulullin and Silindrin were two cauldrons according to the early
                                version of the legendarium in The Book of Lost Tales.</p>
                        </note>
                    </place>

                </listPlace>

            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </xmlHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>Alors vint <persName ref="Yav_001">Palurien</persName>, <persName ref="Yav_001"
                        >Kémi</persName> elle-même, la <persName ref="Yav_001">Dame de la Terre</persName>, épouse d'<persName ref="Aul_001">Aulë</persName>, mère du
                        <orgName ref="Ent_001">seigneur des forêts</orgName>, et elle tissa des
                    sorts autour de ces deux endroits, de profonds enchantements de vie et de
                    croissance et de production de feuilles, de bourgeonnement et de production de
                    fruits - mais elle ne mêla aucun mot qui flétrit à sa chanson. Là ayant chanté
                    elle médita durant un long moment, et les <orgName ref="Val_001">Valar</orgName>
                    s'assirent en cercle autour, et la plaine de <geogName ref="Val_002"
                        >Valinor</geogName> était noire. Puis, après un temps, il vint enfin une
                    vive lueur d'or au milieu de la pénombre, et les <orgName ref="Val_001"
                        >Valar</orgName> élevèrent un cri de joie et de louange, ainsi que toutes
                    leurs compagnies. Voici, de cet endroit qui fut arrosé par <geogName
                        ref="Kul_001">Kulullin</geogName> s'élevait une mince pousse, et de son
                    écorce se déversait une effulguration d'or pâle ; pourtant cette plante poussa
                    en cadence de sorte qu'en sept heures il y eut un arbre d'une puissante stature,
                    et tous les <orgName ref="Val_001">Valar</orgName> et leurs gens pouvaient
                    s'asseoir sous ses branches. De forme très belle et de bonne croissance était ce
                    tronc, et il n'y avait rien qui brisât sa peau sans aspérités, luisant doucement
                    d'une lumière jaune, jusqu'en une vaste hauteur au-dessus de la terre. Alors de
                    belles branches s'élancèrent en toutes directions dans le ciel, et des bourgeons
                    dorés enflèrent sur toutes les brindilles et petites branches, et de ceux-ci
                    jaillirent des feuilles d'un riche vert et aux bordures qui brillaient. Déjà la
                    lumière que produisait cet arbre était large et belle, mais tandis que les
                        <orgName ref="Val_001">Valar</orgName> regardaient il fleurit à vaste
                    produsion, de sorte que toutes ses branches furent cachées par de longues
                    grappes oscillantes de fleurs comme une myriade de lampes de flammes suspendues,
                    et de la lumière tombait des pointes de celles-ci et éclaboussait le sol avec un
                    doux bruit.</p>
                <p>Alors les <orgName ref="Val_001">Dieux</orgName> firent-ils la louange de
                        <persName ref="Van_001">Vana</persName> et <persName ref="Yav_001"
                        >Palurien</persName> et se réjouirent dans la lumière, leur disant : <q
                        who="Val_001" toWhom="Yav_001">"Voici en vérité un très bel arbre, et il
                        doit posséder un nom qui lui soit propre"</q> et <persName ref="Yav_001"
                        >Kémi</persName> dit : <q who="Yav_001" toWhom="Val_001">"Qu'il soit nommé
                            <geogName ref="Lau_001">Laurelin</geogName>, pour l'éclat de sa
                        floraison et la musique de sa rosée"</q>, mais <persName ref="Van_001"
                        >Vana</persName> l'aurait nommé <geogName ref="Lau_001"
                        >Lindeloksë</geogName>, et les deux noms demeurent.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</XML>
